Acknowledgements

The completion of this book is like a long sea journey. Although at times, I felt all by myself, steering my tiny nutshell through storm and bad weather, I was really surrounded by ever so many good forces working towards a safe passage. In the course of my research on textile trade of the Tamil coast with the Portuguese, Dutch, French and English, I came across some documents on slave trade. I continued to look for more and accumulated substantial material during my visits to many archives. I heard the voices of the slaves through the data when I wrote, but it took a long time to complete since I continued to unearth as many documents as possible. The historical records do not remain flat or lack nuance, but give individual expression and emotion, making it easy to understand the journey made by slaves through several agents, brokers, private merchants and East India Companies. This work illustrates the inspiring and interesting study on European slave trading in the Tamil Coast with the markets around the globe and reconstructs the world of human beings who were held captive for an indefinite period of time, coerced into extremely dependent and exploitative power relationships, denied rights (including rights over their labour, lives and bodies) and often vulnerable to forced relocation by various means and forced to labour against their will. The selection of the chapters explains to a large extent, the transcultural, transcontinental and transnational interactions in broad global historical perspective.

I have incurred enormous debts to the generosity, interest, guidance and friendship of a significant number of organizations. As with any project on transoceanic networks, mine was reliant on a global community of support, encouragement and expertise. My greatest debt is to the authorities and staff of Archivo General de Indias, Seville; Rigsarkivet, København; Archiv der Franckesche Stiftungen, Halle; Unitats Archive, Herrnhut; Nationaal Archief, Den Haag; British Library, London; Archives Nationales, Paris; Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris; Centre des Archives d’Outre-Mer, Aix-en-Provence; Archivo General de la Nación, México City; Archivo Histórico del Municipio de Colima, Colima; Family History Library Genealogical Society of Utah, Salt Lake City; Moravian Archives, Bethlehem, Pennsylvania; National Archives of Mauritius, Archives Departmentales de La Reunion, Saint-Denis; Western Cape Archives, Cape Town; Arsip Nasional Republik Indonesia, Jakarta; National Archives of the Philippines, Manila; Sri Lanka National Archives, Colombo; Tamil Nadu State Archives, Chennai; National Archives of India, Puducherry and Historical Archives of Goa, Panaji. As the Corona Virus pandemic devastated the world, my travel came to a halt in January 2020 and I could not collect documents anymore. I had never imagined beforehand such effects of which I had no clue. I am delighted that the book could be completed despite these challenges.

I am grateful to Manohar Publishers for undertaking this publication. It is hoped that the book would advance our understanding of the history of slavery from the Tamil coast connecting various geographical regions with an interest in global history or transnational history including global migrations, interactions and trade routes.

Puducherry

8 December 2024

S. JEYASEELA STEPHEN

CHAPTER 2

The Slaves in Tamil History
and Society

Puranaanuru refers to ilipirappalan (man of low birth) the lower classes and servants in Tamil country, in the ancient period.1 Adimai employed by Tiruvalluvar refers only to a servant of low rank.2 The couplet says that if the citizenry turns indolent, it would enslave them to an enemy king. Hence the view of K.K. Pillay who cites this as the existence of slavery is called into question.3 Many Tamil literary texts such as Pattinapaalai, Maduraikanchi, Pathittrupaththu and Manimekhalai refer to women captured after successful battles.4 Tholkappiyam refers to slavery but it was not widespread.5 Slavery had developed gradually as an institution in the early medieval period. Hence the view of V. Kankasabhai that slavery was unknown to the Tamils may also be questioned.6 Slavery existed in the post-sangam period in some form. Men and women offered themselves as slaves to individuals and families. Since the slaves were apparently the people of the lowest status possible in Tamil society; inscriptions mention their sale or transfer deed to identify them precisely as property. The identity of the slave had been defined and specified just as the exact limits of a piece of land donated to the temple.

Numerous inscriptions mention the terms adiyaar and adiyaazhl (serving) referring to the fact of subordination. It signifies exclusively ‘slave’ rather than indicate another meaning of the term that is ‘devotee’. A record from Tiruchirappalli area mentioned a Chandrasekhara arasa mayinthan of Nandivarman mangalam, the village headman who purchased Ooransolai and her daughter and granddaughter Velanpratti and Amainthankandi by name as kuli azhl (wage labourer) in AD 942. They were employed for six years. He decided to sell them in AD 948 and sold all the three of them to the temple of Vayalur to sing hymns in the temple and be kavarippina varkal (flywhisk women) for the deity.7 Again one finds an inscription of South Arcot area in the early eleventh century which states that the mother of a vellalar was given to be an adiyaazhl for the temple deity and that her son was to be responsible for the cultivation of the temple garden that had been donated.8 Thus vellalars were also donated as slaves to temples and they worked there.

The term adimai had also been used exclusively in inscriptions referring to slave. One inscription mentioned and used the term uvachcha adimai (a male drummer).9 Thus adiyaar, adiyaazhl and adimai had been used interchangeably, referring to slaves. These men and women slaves were un-free, employed in the beginning on a large scale in agriculture and also in the houses. They were given shelter to live in the backyards of the houses, fed and given clothes for maintenance. As these slaves could not be liberated at all they were given or resold and came to be attached to the temples.

Slaves were grouped along with the land and cattle as property and this is revealed from an inscription of AD 1150.10 Another inscription mentions the inheritance right of a slave who was a married woman and had no issue.11 A Brahmin of Nangur possessed 15 men and 7 women slaves and he decided to sell all of them as he could not afford to maintain them anymore. The cultivating tenants of the place in AD 1219 purchased 5 men and 5 women, and paid 1,000 kasus as the price. The buyers were allowed to retain the ownership of slaves on a hereditary basis.12

THE SALE OF SLAVES ENGRAVED ON STONES
AND EMPLOYED BY TEMPLES

The temples in Tamil country became owners of slaves mainly in three ways. At first one finds receipt of slaves whom people had gifted to the temples.13 It is mentioned in a record that a Brahmin who owned slaves had sold 2 women and 5 men for 30 kasus, again 15 persons for 2 kasus, and yet again 6 persons for 13 kasus to the temple. The Brahmin also remitted the entire amount to the temple treasury. The sale of slaves was generally conducted through the registration of a deed on a palm leaf in Tamil prepared at the time to avoid problems and complications in future. In an instance, it is reported that the seal of the aranmani (royal palace) was affixed on a palm leaf record by mistake when slaves were sold. A rectification to this effect was later made by stamping the seal of the temple since the sale of the slaves was done to the temple.14

Secondly, in many cases people voluntarily sold themselves as slaves to the temples. It is reported that eight persons sold themselves in Thanjavur area to a temple but the prices are not stated.15 Two women, their dependents and relatives sold themselves to the same temple; while seven of them were sold for 30 kasus, 15 of them were sold for 30 kasus.16 It is found again that six persons were sold to the same temple for 13 kasus.17 Thus the minimum sale price of a slave was around 2 kasus and the maximum was 4 kasus excluding registration charges of the sale deed. The price of slaves had increased in AD 1175. One finds four devaradiyars who were employed were sold to Tiruvalangadu temple for 700 kasus.18 During the famine of AD 1201, many people had voluntarily become slaves and a vellalan (cultivator) sold himself along with his wife and two daughters to escape starvation after borrowing 110 kasus from temple. It is said that 3 nalis paddy was sold for one kasu which was very expensive at that time and so they had sold themselves.19 Marutha Rajayakondan sold his daughter Ramadevi in AD 1425 to the temple of Ariyamangalam near Tiruchendur.20 Five girls of Rajarajapuram enslaved themselves in AD 1448 to god in Appan temple and settled as irandam kudi (second settlers) of Sermaadevi village.21

Third, it is noticed that temples had come to purchase slaves as they needed them for work.22 An inscription in AD 1196-7 gives a list of 100 slaves purchased by the temple of Viratanesvara both males and females, from several places by an order of the king.23 The slaves sold to temples were marked with sulam (trident).24 They were differentiated from the slaves who belonged to the king marked with ilaicinai.25

The slaves in temples were assigned several duties. Some female slaves dehusked paddy.26 Some washed the clothes.27 Some looked after filling the lamps with oil.28 Thus they did divine services in temples. They were given accommodation, food and clothes for maintenance but not given any wages.

SLAVES SOLD AND EMPLOYED
IN MADAMS

Women attached to a madam in the twelfth century were part of a list of people who were bound themselves in service to the temple in perpetuity.29 A record mentions women given as hereditary servants to a madam at Tiruvaikkali in Thanjavur area in the thirteenth century.30 One finds that a kal thachar (stone mason), his wife and their four sons were sold as adimai (slaves) to the madam at Achutha mangalam in Thanjavur area.31 It is reported in an inscription that Vaiyiradha Rayar had a number of slaves who formed part of the dowry of his wife. He sold them with the consent of his wives to a madam.32 Thus it is seen that men and women who were sold or given to madams in perpetual servitude.

SLAVE SALE DEEDS ON PALM LEAVES: SLAVERY
AND THE SOCIAL HISTORICAL PROCESS

Three palm leaf manuscripts describe in detail the condition of slaves during the period 1509-29. They record that one Thiyagraja Mudaliar sold a slave named Rayaan son of Santhosi, of the parayiar caste in the presence of an arbitrator for 10 pons. Ramachandra Nayinar, a resident of Reddi Kadalangudi village sold four of his slaves called Muthan, Vellichan, his wife Parvathy and a male slave to Subramanya Mudaliar of Manganallur for fourteen pons. Subba Padaychi sold his slaves called Raman, his wife Mukkatai and their children to Appachi Mudaliar of Ganja village for 80 pons. These evidences show that the family as a whole entered into slavery in the Thanjavur region where rice cultivation was intensive.33

These deeds recording the sale of slaves were called aazhl-vilai-piramana-isavu-thittu. The sale was done through an auction and the prices were recorded in the presence of an arbitrator. These manuscripts display the signature of slaves, witnesses and that of the writer of the document.34 A standard clause in the sale deeds was that the slaves were to be property of the purchaser as long as the mountain, river Cauvery, the earth and the grass lasted. The sale of paraiyar had increased in this period. In one instance a family of seven paraiyars was sold for eight and a half pagoda in 1593.35 Most of the slaves in the rural areas were owned by the local elite and wealthier members of the Tamil society. However, it is unclear from records whether owning a slave in that period was perceived as a symbol of social status.

Slavery developed because of socio-economic distress, poverty, famines, drought and debt. According to records, the owners of the slaves found in the medieval sale transactions, were mainly landlords. Thus, the most odious form of private property existed in the form of the sale of human beings. A slave was said to be a saleable person who was then regarded as the property of the buyer. The Tamil society had an open system of slavery with an established hierarchy which placed slaves at the bottom of the social order. Thus there is no lacking of indigenous Tamil primary sources to understand the society than to depend on the accounts of foreigners. Untouchability and slavery came in the way of the material well being of the people and also deprived them of civil rights.

NOTES

1. Puranaanuru, ed. U.V. Swaminatha Aiyar, Madras, 1971, 9: 1-5.

2. Thirukural, ed. M. Virasamy Pillai, Madras, 1849, 608.

3. K.K. Pillay, A Social History of the Tamils, Madras, 1969, rpt. 1975, p. 199.

4. Pattinappaalai, ed. U.V. Swaminatha Aiyar, in Pathupattu, Madras, 1974, line 246; Pathitrupaththu, ed. Avvai Duraisamy Pillai, 2nd edn., South India Saiva Siddhanta Pathippu Kazhagam, Tirunelveli, 1955, song 3, line 9; Manimekhalai, ed. Venkatsamy Nattar, South India Saiva Siddhanta Pathippu Kazhagam, Tirunelveli, 1992, chapter 18, line 119; Maduraikanchi, ed. U.V. Swaminatha Aiyar, in Pathupattu, Madras, 1974, line 583; C. Balasubramanian, The Status of Women in Tamilnadu during the Sangam Age, Madras, University of Madras, 1976.

5. Tholkappiyam, Porul Athikaaram, ed. V.U. Chidambaram Pillai, Madras, 1941, 74.

6. V. Kanakasabhai Pillai, The Tamils Eighteen Hundred Years Ago, Madras, 1966, p. 114. S. Manickam opines that Tamil literary sources on slavery are scanty and they are not corroborated by other evidences. This view is also called into question. S. Manickam, Slavery in Tamil Country—A Historical Overview, CLS, Madras, 1982, p. 25.

7. Annual Report on Epigraphy (including Indian and South Indian Epigraphy from 1881 to 1922, 1923-45, 1950 to 2005), New Delhi/ Madras, 1887-2005 (hereafter ARE), 149 of 1936.

8. South Indian Inscriptions, Publications of the Archaeological Survey of India, vols. I to XXXIV, New Delhi, 1890-1990 (hereafter SII), vol. XXII, no. 141.

9. ARE, 280 of 1927.

10. ARE, 429 of 1918.

11. ARE, 538 of 1918.

12. ARE, 499 of 1904.

13. ARE, 289 of 1910.

14. ARE, 499 of 1904.

15. ARE, 149 of 1937.

16. ARE, 218 of 1925, 219 of 1925.

17. ARE, 217 of 1925.

18. ARE, 80 of 1913.

19. ARE, 86 of 1911.

20. ARE, 365 of 1949.

21. ARE, 638 of 1916.

22. ARE, 223 of 1917.

23. ARE, 230 of 1917.

24. ARE, 230 of 1921.

25. ARE, 141 of 1922.

26. ARE, 122 of 1912

27. ARE, 578 of 1916.

28. ARE, 248 of 1916.

29. ARE, 76 of 1925, 84 of 1925.

30. ARE, 276 of 1925.

31. ARE, 409 of 1925.

32. ARE, 94 of 1926.

33. Kalvettu, vol. 17, pp. 1-6; S. Jeyaseela Stephen, The Coromandel Coast and its Hinterland: Economy, Society and Political System 1500-1600, Delhi, 1997, pp. 180-1.

34. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, The Coromandel Coast, p. 181.

35. ARE, 296 of 1911.

CHAPTER 11

Slaves and Trading Voyages of the
French from Pondicherry and
Karaikal to Mauritius, Reunion
Islands and France, 1687-1792

The French East India Company established a trading factory at Pondicherry in 1674. François Martin took care of the commercial activities of the French Company. He was approached by some local slave dealers in September 1687 who enquired whether he was in need of slaves for export since the Dutch East India Company had been conducting trade in slaves on large scale from the ports of Pulicat, Devanampattinam, Nagapattinam and Tuticorin on the Tamil Coast. Martin replied in the negative, and maintained that it was demeaning for the French to conduct slave trade.1 However, according to records a slave boy of twelve years old had been purchased and exported from Pondicherry in 1687 to the Mascarenes Islands.2

SLAVE TRADE OF THE FRENCH FROM
PONDICHERRY TO MAURITIUS, REUNION
AND THE COMOROS ISLANDS, 1707-1760

After the death of François Martin, the officials of the French Company in Pondicherry decided to conduct slave trade. The company showed interest in the purchase and export of slaves to Isle de Bourbon (Le Reunion) which had been occupied by the French in 1670. The deliberations of the Superior Council of Pondicherry on 9 February 1707 reveal that there was a plan to buy Tamil slaves and export them to Isle de Bourbon.3 For the first time, mention is made of the ship St Louis that sailed away with 25 slaves in September 1707 from Pondicherry.4 Pierre Du Livier, the French Governor of Pondicherry, wrote, a letter to the Directors of the French East India Company in Paris in this regard on 1 October 1707. The next ship sailed from Pondicherry on 17 November 1707 with 4 males and 15 females who were mostly children. They were purchased at six pagodas (around 444 livres) each in Pondicherry the total amount invested was 26,444 livres. In Reunion Island the males were sold for 2,133 livres and the females were sold for 9,030 and the total was 11,163 livres.5 Thus the profit margin was more than fourfold.

The French Governor in Pondicherry took keen interest in the slave trade and asked the Company servants to contact the native dealers for the supply of slaves to be exported on an annual basis. Meanwhile, St Louis returned to Pondicherry in February 1708 and the investment for the purchase of slaves came in the form of silver to the tune of 11,000 piastres from Isle de Bourbon.6 The French Company had paid pagodas (gold coins) to Pondicherry by that time and purchased 6 young girl slaves. Therefore, an order was passed by the French Governor to reimburse the amount in silver bullion. The slaves purchased were transported in ships to Isle de Bourbon under the careful supervision of the ship’s captain. These slave girls reached Bourbon and were employed in the houses prepared for them. The ship La Vierge sailed from Pondicherry in April 1710 and it took 25 slaves. Two slaves died during the voyage. Three were reserved for the French Company and so 20 slaves were sold for 5,667 livres in Reunion.7

According to records, one finds Fr. Senet in Reunion had baptized 12 slaves in 1710. They had come in the ship St. Malo and St. Jean-Baptiste. He also baptized 22 slaves who came in the ship on 27 August 1710. Further he also baptized 3 slaves who came in the ship on 19 October 1710.8

Instructions were sent from Isle de Bourbon to the French Governor in Pondicherry who was requested to send adult slave boys in large numbers to be employed there. As French private merchants were banned from indulging in slave trade, the Directors of the French East India Company in Paris wrote to the Governor in Pondicherry to take all possible care in the export of slaves by the French Company.9 The officials and servants of the French Company in Pondicherry were asked to contact the native slave dealers to ensure the supply of an adequate number of slaves for export to Isle de Bourbon. In the deliberations of the Superior Council of Pondicherry on 6 September 1718, one finds mention of the purchase of slaves in Arcot, the capital of the Nawab. Slaves purchased there were carefully transported to Pondicherry and finally, they were shipped to Isle de Bourbon in 1719.10

Mauritius, abandoned by the Dutch in 1710 and renamed Isle de France was first appropriated by the French in 1715. The island was occupied in 1721 by settlers from the neighbouring Isle de Bourbon. The French Governor in Pondicherry was asked to purchase more slaves for Reunion. He did so and the slaves were exported in ships. It is reported that most of the slaves were between the age of 18 and 25.11

According to records, 200 slaves were purchased and transported in 1737 from Pondicherry to Reunion island. The average length of slave voyages from Pondicherry including days of departure and arrival, was around 44 days.12 There are references to slave mortality owing to disease in 1740. The slaves aboard vessels arriving from Pondicherry died at sea in large numbers and the death rate in 1740 was reported to be 92.5 per cent.13 The French administrators of the Mascarenes Islands had sought agricultural labourers from Pondicherry actively since at least 1728.

TABLE 11.1: EXPORT OF SLAVES FROM PONDICHERRY TO REUNION BY THE FRENCH, 1729-1732

Date of Departure | Number of Slaves
14 February 1729 | 300
27 March 1729 | 173
April 1729 | 26
June 1730 | 45
15 February 1731 | 26
23 November 1731 | 14
24 December 1732 | 4
TOTAL | 588

Source: ADR, C 596, C 599, C 601, C 603.

THE NAWAB OF ARCOT AND HIS POLICY
TOWARDS FRENCH SLAVE TRADE

Since the French East India Company in Pondicherry showed great interest in the purchase and export of slaves overseas, the French Governor wrote a letter to Dost Ali Khan the Nawab of Arcot, seeking permission to purchase and transport slaves. The Nawab replied through his letter dated 5 September 1738 and the text runs as follows:

On what you have prayed to me by your letter asking to give a parwana (temporary permit issued by the provincial officials) that the passage of slaves purchased by you and arrested en route becomes effective. Although it is not our custom to permit any one to buy or take away any slave, I have passed beyond this consideration and have accorded you a parwana, which you have asked me on this subject. Ghulam Hussain Imam Khan made me understand your favourable dispositions by which you have maintained all the liaisons of sincere friendship of which you have frequently given me the mark. This gives me pleasure. You can count on me that I will always give you service whenever I can.14

The Nawab added that ‘we are given to understand that the Governor of Pondicherry was in need of slaves for his port or other places has given order to buy slaves, in some places of my dependency through which these slaves will pass. You would let them pass freely provided that they are not by religion Muslims because that is our wish. You take care that this is executed exactly’.15

The French Company was relieved of the burden of transporting slaves from the villages in the hinterland to the port of Pondicherry. Native slave dealers carried out such works and sold even Muslim slaves. It helped the French to buy, transport and export Tamil Muslim slaves officially in the ships of the Company violating the order of the Nawab of Arcot.

METHODS OF OBTAINING SLAVES FOR
FRENCH OVERSEAS EXPORT

Entries found in the Tamil diaries maintained by the natives of Pondicherry mention slave dealers and the ways in which they managed to obtain slaves for supply to the French East India Company. Slaves were purchased at Bahoor, Ozhundiyapattu, Vriddachalam and Tiruvalanjuli and brought to Pondicherry for export. The price of a child was 10 pagodas while that of an adult was 15, and a female was 20 pagodas. These slave agents enticed many woodcutters through business conversations on the pretext of buying timber. Then they trapped them in the warehouses or lodged them in private buildings when needed, feeding them regularly and finally selling them off as slaves mercilessly to the French Company for export to Mauritius.16 Even the French Company officials, on a number of occasions, intimidated, kidnapped and lured men, women and children immigrating for menial jobs with the help of native slave dealers. A man in Pondicherry revealed that he was inveigled into the building, on the promise of being employed as a coolie (wage labourer) to carry a bag and that when he entered, he was arrested, his head was shaved, fetters were placed round his legs and he was declared a slave. Another man announced that he was offered betel, lightly smeared with lime and when he chewed the betel leaf he felt giddy. Thereafter, he did not know what happened to him. On becoming conscious, he found that he was led away and found himself as a slave being sold to the French Company in Pondicherry.17

Slave dealers were skilled kidnappers who were in the regular habit of luring people who lived in villages. There was a separate house in a hamlet (name not mentioned) located west of Tranquebar town, where batches of 50 and 100 individuals were imprisoned and kept. They were transported silently at night in a boat to reach Ariyankuppam situated in the environs of Pondicherry. These slaves were confined again in a house belonging to Paramanandan, a great slave dealer. The heads of the slaves were shaved and they were given black clothes to wear. Each slave had a fetter placed around one of his legs. They were fed with canjee (boiled rice with water) and had to remain there until a sailing vessel came to take them away to the French islands near Africa.18

It had been reported that Paramanandan, the great slave dealer had kidnapped and arrested 4 chetti (trading caste) men and 1 chetti woman in 1743. He transported them by a boat to Ariyankuppam where the slaves spent a night in a house, and were then removed to another one which belonged to Louis Jude who divulged under Cornet, the keeper of the warehouse in the fort of Pondicherry. Some chettis who visited Louis Jude in connection with some textile business happened to see the slaves in his house, and questioned him. He said that he had purchased the slaves recently. When the chettis asked for further details, especially regarding the castes to which the slaves belonged, he became nervous and said that he would send them away if they were chettis. The news spread among the chettis and others and also reached the officials of the French Company, who sent some peons to the house of Louis Jude, who divulged the information. It was found that the slaves were chettis. The peons of the French Company searched for Paramanandan and pounced on him in the town. They arrested and produced him before the judge in the court. He ordered Paramanandan to be thrown into prison for he had trapped the chettis, the merchant caste, as slaves.19 The native slave agents were greedy for money and, therefore, indulged in immoral traffic. They used unethical ways to supply slaves to the French Company as there was demand for slave exports from Pondicherry. Thus, slaves were trapped largely through deception, coercion and kidnapping by unscrupulous native agents. Arulanandan (Arlanden in French records) was another slave dealer who appeared in a case heard by the Superior Council of Pondicherry in 1743, where he was accused of illegal slave-trading and described as the valet/ dubashi and broker of Louis Jude, the French merchant.20

SHIPPING SLAVES FROM TO MAURITIUS,
REUNION AND THE COMOROS

Periodic slave exports by the French from Pondicherry in the eighteenth century show that children and young adults, many of whom had been kidnapped and sold into bondage, comprised the majority of slaves. Wars and famines forced desperate men and women to sell themselves or their children into slavery. When Chanda Sahib pillaged the region of Thanjavur in October 1738, the servants and officials of the French Company made captives and sent them as slaves to Mauritius. Due to continued droughts, slave trade thrived in the Cauvery Delta area. Slaves were purchased in the hinterland and came to be transported secretly to Pondicherry for export. In his diary entry on 25 June 1743, Ananda Ranga Pillai the chief dubash of the French Governor, mentioned that having developed direct overseas trade from Pondicherry to Port Louis, the French Company transported slaves in ships. The French also re–exported slaves who came from Pondicherry in ships to Mauritius to other places like the Comoros Islands located at the northern end of the Mozambique Channel. In 1743, the ship St Pierre directly sailed away from Pondicherry with plenty of slaves to the Comoros.21 Another ship St Benoit had also directly sailed from Pondicherry to the Comoros in 1744 with slaves.22

In line with the metropolitan policy, the Superior Council of Pondicherry issued an order on 12 January 1742 instructing all Christian slave owners in Pondicherry to baptize their slaves within a year from that date. It was added that all slaves should be educated properly in the Catholic faith.23 In 1746, the Superior Council of Pondicherry passed another order that no slave would be allowed to work on Sundays and Christian holidays without permission.24 Ships with slaves sailed regularly from Pondicherry, and it was estimated that 20-5 per cent of them died en route to the Comoros islands.25 There were 870 Tamil slaves in Mauritius (out of the total population of 12,196 slaves) in 1761. Thus, 7 per cent of the population of Mauritius comprised Tamil slaves.26

TABLE 11.2: SAILINGS WITH SLAVES FROM
PONDICHERRY TO MAURITIUS, 1729-1945

Year | Number of Ship
1729 | Indien
1730 | St. Pierre
1731 | Dauphin
1731 | St. Joseph
1732 | St. Joseph
1734 | St. Pierre
1744 | St. Benoit
1744 | Pondichéry
1745 | Brilliant

Source: ADR, Alfred Martineau, ed., Correspondance du Conseil Supérieur de Pondichéry et de la Compagnie, 1726-67, 6 vols., Pondichéry, 1920-31; Edmond Gaudart, ed., Procès–verbaux des délibèrations du Conseil Supérieur de Pondichéry du 1 er Fevrier 1701 au 31 Decembre 1739, 3 vols., Pondichéry, 1913-15.

PONDICHERRY SLAVE IN FRANCE IN 1750
AND THE LEGAL BATTLE DURING 1759

Francisco (Francisque in French record) was born to parents of Indo-Portuguese origin and lived in Pondicherry. He was taken as a slave to France in a ship that sailed from Pondicherry in 1750 by a trader of the French East India Company who lived in the port of St. Malo. After serving for 7 years in the house of his master he ran away because of mistreatment. Later he sought another employer in 1757. His former master had him imprisoned and Francisco sued for his freedom, first in the Admiralty Court of France and then, upon appeal, before the Parliament of Paris.27

It is interesting to find that the lawyer of Francisco argued in 1759 for his freedom on the grounds of his Indian origins, the free soil principle and failure to comply with the Code Noir of 1685, the ordinance of 23 April 1615, the edict of 1716, edicts of July and September 1720, letters patents of 1723, the edict of 1724 and the declaration of 15 December 1738. The lawyer argued for the chief claim for an exclusive relationship between slavery and blackness. It was a more significant feature on the racialized nature of slavery then present in the French empire. Interestingly, the lawyer of Francisco had never quoted the 1739 order, despite the fact that it had been issued two decades earlier.28 This was a crucial piece of legislation for claim to freedom and the order, issued by King Louis XV on 2 March 1739, prohibited the enslavement of Indians. It was also counter argued that French laws prohibiting the enslavement of Indians applied to American Indians, and not those of South Asia. The case did not drag on for years and the final judgement was delivered in favour of Francisco. This is the first metropolitan legal case which argued that slavery was justifiable only for Africans and their descendents, not to Indians or Indo-Portuguese/Indo-Europeans before the Parliament of Paris in 1759.

SLAVES FROM KARAIKAL TO PONDICHERRY
AND THE GROWTH OF SLAVE TRADE OF
THE FRENCH COMPANY, 1760-1778

After the seizure of Pondicherry on 16 January 1760 by the English East India Company, the French began to pay attention to Karaikal. They began to trade and purchased and exported slaves. A document of the French Company mentions that the price of a slave in Karaikal was around 3-4 Porto Novo pagodas in 1760.29 Owing to the unavailability of adult slaves, the slave agents in Karaikal arranged for the sale of kids and children. A child, 2½ years old, was sold for 3 pagodas in January 1767. A girl, 9 years old, was purchased for 4 pagodas in March 1774. Girls, 8 years of age, were purchased for 3 pagodas and sometimes also for 3 panams. There was a mention of 2 boys aged 12 and 16, who were purchased for 6 and 16 pagodas respectively.30 Another French record mentioned the sale of a male slave for 53 Arcot rupees in August 1769. The purchase price of slaves had been high, and was escalating at an alarming rate. The main reason was the heavy demand for slaves in Mauritius and Le Reunion by the French East India Company.

Names and castes are neatly mentioned in the sale deeds of slaves at Karaikal. Kumaran of the vellala caste remitted his son aged 12 to Appu. The father received 3½ pagodas for the transfer of his son on 8 November 1774.31 Further, names like Veera, a boy of the pariayar caste and another called Pungaavanam, are mentioned. A slave, 10 years old was sold at Karaikal in 1774 for 50 rupees (20 pagodas). Naagaatha of the vellala caste sold her daughter Kamalayee.32 It is interesting to find several buyers whose names often appear and they were French. It includes Ange Marie Nicolaz, the notary clerk of Karaikal (mentioned in 4 sale deeds), Alexandres de Rosaire (mentioned in 3 sale deeds) and Poly d’Aurbigny, the master-surveyor of Karaikal (mentioned in 3 sale deeds). Those slaves who were of vellalar caste exported to Mauritius, were employed in the plantations on arrival as they were professionally skilled in agricultural operations.

TABLE 11.3: SALE OF SLAVES FROM KARAIKAL FOR
EXPORT TO MAURITIUS AND REUNION, 1766-1776

Year | Male | Female | Total
1766 | – | 1 | 1
1767 | – | 1 | 1
1771 | 1 | – | 1
1774 | 20 | 17 | 37
1775 | 3 | 2 | 5
1776 | 2 | 2 | 4

Source: Edmond Gaudart, Catalogue des manuscrits des ancienns archives de l’Inde Française, 1690-1789, 8 vols., Pondichéry, 1926-42.

Pondicherry was restored to the French in 1765 and there were attempts in 1768 to purchase slaves for export. The French Company transported 329 slaves from Pondicherry to Mascarenes till 1775.33 The noirs (adult males) and caporl (young males) were sent in large numbers as slaves. No young women were exported in this period. Pondicherry was again occupied by the English from August 1778 to February 1785.34 Therefore, the slave trade of the French East India Company to Mauritius and Le Reunion came to a halt.

The customs duty on the export of slaves had been 4 per cent in Pondicherry since 1715. The French Company raised it from time to time with the aim of increasing the revenue. They also reduced the rate sometimes with a motive to attract traders. During January 1739, the Superior Council of Pondicherry ordered ½ per cent ad valorem duty to be levied on slaves brought into Pondicherry for export. A writer was appointed in Pondicherry, at the port, to maintain the accounts of customs duties on exports including slaves.35

HUMAN MERCHANDISE AT THE MARKET:
INSIGHTS FROM THE SLAVE REGISTER
OF PONDICHERRY

Though there is a lack of exact information regarding the conditions which determined the price of a slave in Pondicherry, there are some clues which are available. The price of a slave was determined by his/her age, skills and physical appearance. Slaves who were skilled cooks, carpenters and masons, were more valuable than unskilled slaves. Adult and good looking slaves were also more expensive than children or older slaves. Ananda Ranga Pillai, the chief dubash, mentioned in his private diary that the age of the native slaves primarily determined their value in the market. Those above 7 years and below 16 years of age had fetched a high price in the Indo-French town of Pondicherry. A Tamil document dated 25 November 1781, preserved in the southern zonal office of the National Archives of India, Pondicherry, describes some of the procedures followed in the sale of slaves in Pondicherry.36 In the open slave market in Pondicherry, the slaves were present with their masters. Auction was conducted by public outcry and the slaves were sold. The sale transactions were confirmed through the registration of a deed. It was executed in the presence of the local officials along with the deposition mentioning that the absolute right over the slave vested with the buyer. The sale deed was written both in Tamil and French by the ur kanakkar (accountant of the place). The witnesses also signed the document. The money receipt was made by the chavadi ur kanakkar (court accountant of the place), and it was executed in the chavadi (court) of Pondicherry. On the sale of slaves, the French and other Europeans besides the natives in Pondicherry had to pay 5 per cent by way of tax and 1½ per cent for stamp paper.37

The French East India Company’s sale register of the native slaves in Pondicherry contains the name of the slave, his or her probable age, place of origin along with the place from where the slave was brought, the name of the slave dealer, relationship if any, the name of the seller, the exact price for which the slave was sold, the date of sale, and the purchaser’s name. It is learnt that children were sold in the auction only after consent was obtained from the mothers/grandmothers. The price varied between 3 rupees and 21 rupees. The percentage of sale of the male slaves was more than that of the female slaves.38 The buyers included the Muslims (Mohammed Shah on 11 September 1783, Mohammed Thasty on 22 August 1783 and Khader Sahib on 4 September 1790), the Indo-Portuguese (Francisco Rodrigues on 12 September 1783) and the Hindus who had come from distant places (like Thondiayarpettai near Madras and Sriperumbudur) to participate in the auction in Pondicherry.39

According to the slave register, 149 slaves were sold in Pondicherry in 1783. The number decreased in the following years.40 We find frequent mention of individuals like Muthu, Nalla Thamby, Thailamme and Muthammal, slave dealers who had been participating in the sale of slaves in Pondicherry. Khader Sahib was found selling as well as buying slaves on different dates (3 December 1783 and 18 December 1783). The police chief in Pondicherry had issued regulations for the sale of slaves on 20 June 1778 since several complaints were lodged in the town. Additional rules were enforced on 18 December 1790 to avoid the problems encountered in slave purchases and sales. Large scale illegal slave sale transactions necessitated such measures in the town.41 It was ordered that the sale deeds of slaves must be signed by the mothers or grandmothers, and not by the father. It is significant that mothers and grandmothers enjoyed the sole authority to relegate children to slave status. The local advisor also played his part.

TABLE 11.4: GEOGRAPHICAL ORIGIN OF SLAVES AND
THE SELLING PRICE IN PONDICHERRY, 1783

Date | Place | Price in Rupees
13 July 1783 | Kosapalayam | 21
18 July 1783 | Madras | 4
24 July 1783 | Muthirapalayam | 10
28 July 1783 | Arcot | 4
28 July 1783 | Villupuram | 15
28 July 1783 | Yembalam | 7½
2 August 1783 | Nellikuppam | 10
2 August 1783 | Villiyanallur | 4
10 August 1783 | Kalapet | 5½
11 August 1783 | Kanchipuram | 15
12 August 1783 | Sipouvanthittu | 4
23 August 1783 | Kumbakonam | 5
25 August 1783 | Panruti | 3
26 August 1783 | Thiruvennainallur | 3
26 August 1783 | Chingleput | 64

Source: National Archives of India, Puducherry, Eighteenth Century Documents, folder no. 91.

The French East India Company in Pondicherry requested the weavers to produce guineas and salempouris that had been used as slave cloth. The same varieties were exported to Mauritius, Le Reunion, the Mascarenes and the Comoros islands for the use of slaves. Ananda Ranga Pillai supplied 1,500 pieces of slave shirts which were in great demand in the Mascarenes. Slave trade conducted by the French had facilitated the production of the coarse variety of cloth. There was a heavy demand for striped and checked guinea cloth required for clothes for the slaves. The slave cloth of gurras (coarse cloth), futas (strong and cheap calico) and niqnarias (stripped calico patterned in loom with 14¼ cubits long and 11/8 cubits broad) produced in Pondicherry, were exported for the use of slaves.42 Many Tamil slaves exported to Mauritius worked as cooks and household servants and helped the French population. Slaves also worked as palanquin bearers since 4-6 of them were needed for each vehicle.

Trade and traffic in slaves was abolished by the French National Assembly through a decree and it also came into force in Pondicherry from 1 November 1792 through the arrêtés (orders) of 11, 14 and 15 October 1792.43 The Colonial Assembly of Pondicherry asked the natives in the town to dispose of the slaves acquired earlier. It also banned them from doing business in slaves. Thus, with the abolition of slavery in Pondicherry in 1792, the export of slaves to Mauritius and Le Reunion came to an end.

ESCAPE OF A TAMIL SLAVE FROM MAURITIUS
TO PONDICHERRY IN A SHIP IN 1785

Slaves exported from Pondicherry to Mauritius were treated as private property. João (John) was a slave exported from Pondicherry to Mauritius and he served Lousteau his master for many years. A complaint was lodged by Lousteau at the police station in Port Louis, Mauritius, on 25 May 1785 wherein he stated that João his slave had been abducted. He also mentioned that his fugitive slave was of the lascar caste, a Tamil, dark in complexion, short in height, with a handsome, slightly thin face, a gentle appearance, long hair, abundantly endowed with clothes such as jackets and shorts, wearing small gold earrings and a pin with a gold heart on his shirt and having on the arm, a mark which read DM.44

On enquiry the police learnt that João the slave, was a skilled carpenter. He had managed to escape and sailed away in the ship Le Brilliant that left Port Louis on 20 May 1785 to Pondicherry. João had boarded the ship by mentioning himself as a freeman under the name of Joseph. On 16 December 1785, the police received information regarding João being in the service of M. Brousse, a lieutenant of the regiment of Isle de France, with whom he had disembarked in Pondicherry.45 In spite of the fact that João was asked to be deported to Mauritius, nothing happened. He lived happily in Pondicherry and did not return. The French Company officials in Pondicherry could not take any effective steps in this case because there was no provision in the then prevailing legal system.

The Hindu slaves of Pondicherry in Mauritius who survive in records is because a significant proportion of slave owners were Hindus. In 1775, Muthu a free Tamil man owned a slave named Rama and he reported his death at 80 years.46 Hindus were also kidnapped. In 1785 several Indians testified before the police in Port Louis calling for the liberation of Aadiya Paatham (Odia Padam) a Tamil who had been kidnapped by Jean de Silvas in 1775 and enslaved. It was reported to the police. Several Tamils testified before the police in Port Louis for liberation.47 Hindu slave owners had ill-treated the slaves and committed acts of wanton cruelty. Chinna Thambi (Sinetamby), a free Indian in Mauritius had been described as a man of very bad character. In a local police report he described the suicide of one of his slaves, attributing to his harsh treatment. The police could not arrest him because there was no evidence and the needed proof. Chinna Thambi, on another occasion had been reported to ill-treat Arunachalan (Arnacelon) one of his Tamil slaves who was badly wounded with his arms bound. The slave was sent for medical treatment and the cost was charged to Chinna Thambi.48 Jean Baptiste Pipon a French merchant in Mauritius mentioned a transaction involving three slaves, very handsome and aged between 12 and 18, who had been purchased in Pondicherry. He also mentioned the arrival of a female slave from Pondicherry in 1791 and advised the prospective buyer to do the needful immediately.49 In 1792, three French vessels sailed from Pondicherry to the Mauritius with 1,200 slaves.50 The French Company was able to obtain more slaves from the Cuddalore area and so two more French ships sailed away from Pondicherry with 300 Tamil slaves and the ship arrived at Mauritius on 3 February 1792.51

CONCLUSION

The French East India Company exported slaves from Pondicherry, Cuddalore and Karaikal areas to Mauritius, Reunion and Comoros Islands. The French Company attempted to enter into agreements with the port officials and rulers of the Tamil Coast requesting a legal stamp for the purchase and transport of slaves but it was of no use. However, religion had played an important role in slave trade. While the Nawab of Arcot desired that Muslims should not be exported as slaves and the European missionaries also wished not to export the slaves who became Christians.

In the beginning of the eighteenth century, the French Company preferred young slaves for overseas export so that they might lose memory of their parents and forget their own native place and knew nothing of what had happened when they were young. There would be a tendency also in that case not to run away from the masters and be very obedient and submissive. Natural calamities such as the failure of crops, drought and famine had been key factors for persons becoming slaves voluntarily. The relationship between lack of rainfall and food scarcity perhaps was the cause of rise for the slave market on the Tamil Coast. The slave supplies dried up when famine situation disappeared. The monetary value of slaves fluctuated over time and depended on age, gender, skills and market demands.

NOTES

1. Lotika Varadarajan, India in the Seventeenth Century: Memoirs of François Martin (hereafter Memoirs), 2 vols., Delhi, 1984, vol. II, pt. I, p. 1070.

2. Hubert Gerbeau, ‘Des minorités mal connues: Esclaves indiens et malais des Mascareignes au XIXe siècle’, in Migrations, minorités et échanges en Océan Indien, XIXe-XXe siècle, Aix-en-Provence: IHPOM, 1979, pp. 160-242.

3. Archives Nationales (hereafter AN), Paris, MSS Colonies Série C^2, no.12, fol. 219; See also MSS Colonies Série C^2, no. 68, fol. 214.

4. Bibliothèque Nationale de Paris (henceforth BNP), MSS Nouvelles Acquisitions Françaises (hereafter NAFR), no. 8929, fol. 275.

5. Archives Departmentales de la Reunion (hereafter ADR), Saint-Denis, C 2791, fls. 81r-82v.

6. BNP, MSS Fond Français, Memoire sur la Compagnie des Indes Orientales, no. 6231, fol. 39.

7. ADR, C 2792, fl. 9r.

8. ADR, GG 1, Saint-Paul nos. 748-756, 758-780, 782-783.

9. AN, MSS Colonies Série C^2, no. 72, fols. 141-2.

10. Edmond Gaudart, ed., Procès-verbaux des délibèrations du Conseil Supérieur de Pondichéry du 1 er Fevrier 1701 au 31 Decembre 1739 (hereafter Procès-verbaux), 3 vols., Pondichéry, 1913-15, see 6 September 1718.

11. ADR, C 319.

12. Richard B. Allen, ‘The Constant Demand of the French: The Mascarene Slave Trade and the Worlds of the Indian Ocean and Atlantic during the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries’, Journal of African History, no. 49, 2008, pp. 43-72, see p. 65.

13. J.M. Filliozat, La Traite des Escalves vers le Mascareignes au XVIII e Siecle, Paris, 1974, p. 226.

14. Alfred Martineau, Lettres & Conventions des Gouverneurs de Pondichéry, avec differents princes hindous (1666 a 1793), Pondichéry, 1914, p. 58.

15. Ibid., p. 57.

16. Frederick Price, H. Dodwell and V. Rangachari, eds., The Private Diary of Ananda Ranga Pillai, Dubash to Joseph François Dupleix, Knight of the Order of St. Michael, and Governor of Pondicherry: A Record of Matters Political, Historical, Social, and Personal, from 1736 to 1761 (hereafter ARP Diary), vol. I, 1904; vol. II, 1907; vol. III, 1914; vol. IV, 1916; vol. V, 1917; vol. VI, 1918; vol. VII, 1919; vol. VIII, 1922; vol. IX, 1924; vol. X, 1925; vol. XI, 1927; vol. XII, 1928, Madras; repr., Delhi, 1980, vol. I, pp. 227–30.

17. ARP Diary, vol. I, pp. 228–30.

18. Ibid. Ananda Ranga Pillai had mentioned that Paramananda Pillai of Karaikal was a rich merchant. He also said that Ramalinga Pillai of Karaikal was wealthy. ARP Diary, vol. IX, pp. 248-50.

19. Ibid., vol. I, pp. 227-30.

20. Centre des Archives d’Outre-Mer (hereafter CAOM), Aix-en-Provence, Inde, Série M/91.

21. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, ‘Waves of Migration of Tamil Slaves and Skilled Artisans from Puducherry to Mauritius and Le Reunion under the French East India Company, 1707-93’, Journal of the Institute of Asian Studies, vol. xxv, no. 2, March 2008, pp. 41-63, see p. 47.

22. Edmond Gaudart, La criminalite dans les comptoirs français del’Inde au XVIIIe siecle, Pondichéry, 1937, p. 17.

23. Edmond Gaudart, Catalogue des manuscrits des ancienns archives de l’Inde Française, 1690-1789, 8 vols., Pondichéry, 1926-42, vol. I, p. 9; Edmond Gaudart, Procès-verbaux 1747, document no. 29.

24. CAOM, Inde, B/28 and B/29. For more on the baptisms of French owned slaves, see CAOM, FM, F^3/238, fols. 525-6.

25. Marina Carter, ‘Indian Slaves in Mauritius, 1729-1834’, The Indian Historical Review, vol. XV, nos. 1-2, 1988-9, pp. 233-47.

26. CAOM, Aix-en-Provence, DFC, Memoire no. 132, Extrait du recensement general de l ‘Isle de France, 1761.

27. Mémoire signifié pour le nommé Francisque, Indien de nation, néophyte de l’Eglise Romaine, Intimé contre le Sieur Allain-François-Ignace Brignon, se disant Ecuyer, Appellan, Chez P.G. Simon, Imprimeur du Parlement, Paris, 1759.

28. Ibid.

29. British Library (hereafter BL), London, Oriental and India Office Collection (hereafter OIOC), The Verlee Collection, 1769-1836, MSS EUR. F. 193, fol. 6, see the accounts of M. Bretel in August 1769.

30. CAOM, Aix-en-Provence, Feuilles Volantes, Karaikal, Serie Le-Indes, dossier nos. 3356, 3422, 3540, 3640, 3657, 3810 and 3871.

31. Edmond Gaudart, Catalogue des manuscrits, vol. IV, p. 144.

32. Ibid., vol. V, document no. 3648.

33. Richard B. Allen, ‘The Constant Demand’, p. 55, see Table 4.

34. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, ‘Urbanism and the Chequered Existence of the Indo-French Town of Pondicherry, 1674-1793’, Revue Historique de Pondichéry, vol. XIX, 1996, pp. 29-64.

35. W.H. Dalgliesch, The Company of the Indies in the Days of Dupliex, Easton, 1933, p. 68.

36. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, ‘Puduvai Avana Kapagathil Ore Adimai Sasanam’, Avanam, vol. 8, 1997, p. 96. The sale deed in Tamil was executed by Tayilaamma, the wife of Ponnanan of the palli caste in favour of Mariyamma.

37. National Archives of India, Puducherry (hereafter NAIP), Eighteenth Century Documents, folder no. 449, fol. 3.

38. ARP Diary, vol. XII, p. 18; vol. I, p. 269.

39. NAIP, Eighteenth Century Documents, folder no. 91, Vented’ enfants et d’ d’esclaves, 25 November 1781 to 22 December 1791.

40. Ibid.

41. Plaidoyer de M. Ed. Thureau, Indien, de l’esclavage et de la traite des Indiens, Paris, 1844, pp. 17-18.

42. S. Jeyaseela Stephen, Oceanscapes, p. 490.

43. BNP, LK 19.18.

44. National Archives of Mauritius, Coromandel, Serie JB, 47, Procedure Criminelle, 1785, Evasion of João the slave of M. Lousteau.

45. Ibid.

46. CAOM, Aix-en-Provence, Registre Etat Civil, Isle de France.

47. Sadasivam Reddi, ‘Aspects of Indian Culture in Ile de France between 1803 and 1810’, in History, Memory and Identity, eds., Vijayalakshmi Teelock and Edward A. Alpers, Nelson Mandela Centre, Mauritius, 2001, p. 35.

48. M. Jumeer, Les Affranchis et les Indiens Libres à l’Ile de France au xviiième siècle 1721-1803, University of Poitiers Thesis, 1984, pp. 277-80.

49. Auguste Toussaint, Le Mirage des Iles: Le negoce français aux Mascareignes au XVIIIe siècle, Aix-en-Provence, 1977, p. 94.

50. British Library (hereafter BL), Oriental and India Office Collection (hereafter OIOC), P/241/31, fl.562, letter of Mathew Yeats to Sir Charles Oakley dated 22 December 1792.

51. BL, OIOC, P/241/36, fls. 6-19, the letter of Mathew Yeats to Major-General William Meadows, dated 3 February 1792.